<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>c | Simon Renger</title><link>/tags/c/</link><atom:link href="/tags/c/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>c</description><generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Simon Renger 2022</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2021 14:10:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><image><url>/img/icon-192.png</url><title>c</title><link>/tags/c/</link></image><item><title>Internship at OurMachinery</title><link>/project/themachinery/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2021 14:10:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>/project/themachinery/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="http://www.ourmachinery.com">The Machinery&lt;/a> is a lightweight hackable modern game engine, written
in plain C.Written in plain C. Boots instantly. Responsive UI. Recompiles in seconds. Supports hot
reloading everywhere. Made to be hacked. Extend or modify with plugins. The flexibility of a custom
engine with the convenience of a ready-made one.Maximum performance. Fiber-based job system. Modern
rendering architecture.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="my-main-responsibilities">My main responsibilities&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Tools Engineering&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>During my internship I have been in charge for multiple improvements of the UX of the Editor. I have
introduced different views to the Asset Browser, which are modeled after the Windows Explorer: Grid,
List, Detail View. Besides, I have introduced the concept of asset labels, which allows for quick
grouping assets together with labels. Also the user can filter with those labels assets.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The bigger tasks was to introduce a Debugger to our Visual Scripting language. This was were most of
my time went. I introduced breakpoints, flow visualization, step through and a watch value functionality.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>QA Engineering&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I am working with GitHub Actions. It verifies that our engine can be built on Windows (&lt;code>msvc&lt;/code> and
&lt;code>clang-cl&lt;/code>) and Linux (our test environment is Ubuntu) with the clang tool chain. Besides I have
been adding functionality of integration tests to the CI system on the server, Integration tests and
unit tests are running side by side in specific intervals (Unit tests every commit or PR)&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>